there's one massive study that changed
everything about how we understand blood
pressure in fact it was so influential
that it was stopped early it's also
changed my perspective on blood pressure
in even more drastic ways which I'll
also explain you see in the past blood
pressure recommendations were set to 140
over 90 that's the systolic and
diastolic numbers on a blood pressure
reading these numbers correspond to the
maximum pressure in your artery so
systolic and the minimum pressure as the
heart relaxes so diastolic then a study
released that completely obliterated the
idea of 140 over 90 that's this study in
this study the researchers randomly
assigned over 9,000 cardiovascular
disease atrisk people to one of two
groups a standard blood pressure
lowering treatment or an intensive blood
pressure lowering treatment the
difference between the two groups was
the amount of medication given the only
distinguishing factor between the groups
was to achieve less than 140 units for
systolic blood pressure in those on the
standard treatment and to achieve around
120 units for systolic in those in the
intensive treatment we can see that they
achieved that over several years the
standard treatment as indicated by the
vertical axis maintain blood pressure
under 140 and the intensive treatment
maintain blood pressure around 120 so
what happened if we look at the data we
see both treatments standard in blue and
the Intensive in Orange the higher the
lines go the more cardiovascular events
like heart attack stroke heart failure
and death occur you can see that at the
oneyear Mark well there's no difference
yet even one more year later and
definitely three years later the results
are clear the intensive treatment
condition were at a much lower risk
about 25% lower than the standard
treatment condition in fact the evidence
was so clear the researchers had to stop
the study early because it's unethical
to continue when the evidence strongly
indicates intensive treatment should be
offered to the other group so since then
blood pressure recommendations have been
reduced to 120 over 80 technically
getting under that and that's where I
think more emphasis needs to be made
because as far as I'm aware it's not
like we know that 120 over 80 is the end
all be all we know it's better than a
higher blood pressure but we don't know
if it's just it as I don't know 100 over
60 for example and my two cents is that
the lower you can get your blood
pressure the better now before someone
with very low blood pressure starts
slamas me about their struggles I'm
talking about cardiovascular disease
it's true that too low of blood pressure
can cause their own issues which we'll
get into because the results of this
study were not all Rosy there were
downsides however on a cardiovascular
health front it seems reasonable to me
that the lowest a person's blood
pressure can be with a key emphasis on
while still being able to function
normally the better there are points at
which low blood pressure can be a
problem and the researchers outlined a
few problems that participants
experienced on this intensive
treatment there's some finer details of
this study that I'll be going over in my
research review that I wrote for the
physionic Insiders if you're so inclined
to learn more you can join through the
link in the description you also get
access to all my work along with a
monthly podcast distilling everything
down for you and a premium email list so
that I send you all the most important
actionable information okay enough
marketing so there's this table and
don't let your eyes glaze over I'm only
going to highlight a few things here as
a quick reference if uh these numbers on
the far right under P value are less
than 0.05 it indicates a statistically
significant effect or in less statistics
terms there's a likely effect happening
between the groups now I'll bring your
attention to hypotention and Syncopy
they're related essentially passing out
an overly low blood pressure was
experienced by some people in the
intensive treatment group at a higher
rate than those in the standard
treatment however if I point out one
more thing acute kidney injury was also
more frequent in the intensive treatment
group about 70% increase so why might
all this be well the low blood pressure
and passing out makes sense simply
because that's the nature of
artificially reducing blood pressure
through drugs however the kidney damage
is explained by the researchers as one
of two things well one some blood
pressure medications are diuretics they
flush water out of the body as well as
drugs that directly affect the kidneys
like Angiotensin converting enzyme
Inhibitors we don't need to get into the
details other than some drugs directly
Target the kidneys these drugs could
have temporarily affected kidney
function the second explanation is due
to low blood pressure the kidneys
receiving less blood called perfusion
which could also cause kidney damage so
where does that leave us confused
concerned well let's address it this
indicates that possibly kidney specific
blood pressure medications should be
avoided more specifically if your
compound multiple medications for blood
pressure since the Intensive group was
taking three and if you look at the
supplemental data over 1,000 people were
on four or more medications so one might
still be good to go but as you add more
the risk may increase we also don't know
if this applies to all blood pressure
medications or just kidney specific ones
I wish that the researchers had done a
subgroup analysis to tease out some of
those specifics alas they did not so
what are the key takeaways here the main
point of this study is that reducing
your blood pressure to less than 120
over 80 is a huge benefit to your
cardiovascular health however as it
seems to also be indicated by this study
trying to do that without blood pressure
medication that affects the kidneys is
preferable and being on many blood
pressure medications may cause harm to
the kidneys an area that still needs to
be investigated more so how does one
reduce their blood pressure then well if
you're interested in the easiest
exercise that has a potent effect check
this out and if you're interested in
taking a supplement or adding some
things to your diet instead check this
out I'll see you over there